[SPEAKER_01]: So, you always emphasize that it's important to question why we're doing what we're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, trying to practice to abandon sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's important, in order to do that properly, to understand what the problem with sensuality actually is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I thought an interesting way of framing that reflection might be, what would hypothetically have to change in order for sensuality to no longer be a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I think the main, the main thing would be, like, hypothetically, if sensuality, sensual desire, engaging with sensual desire, if that would not have the effect, the same effect on citta that it has, then it wouldn't be a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, you know, sometimes people say, it's like, oh, sensuality, it's because it's harming others and stuff, but you can get sensual desire that don't involve others, that don't really harm others, but you cannot have sensual desires that do not harm the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, when I say harm the mind, I don't mean it's like some obvious torture or torment inflicted because of the sensual desire, but I mean in a subtle way,
[SPEAKER_01]: The sensuality is that which keeps the animal liable to be affected by everything else that it will experience through the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's impossible to engage with sensuality without reinforcing that very nature of wilderness of that animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: The best example would be, as I gave it many times, like the suttas, you gave a wild elephant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sensuality is what keeps it wild.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, obviously, a lot of sensuality, a lot of non-restraint will make it even wilder.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really, the question, like, why is sensuality a problem, then, should be reframed as, like, why is having a wild mind a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: At least to some degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when I say wild, I don't mean only the the one extreme of that wilderness.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean even a little bit traces of old wilderness tendencies.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they are left, they are a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as there is at least a degree of sensuality that's not being perceived as dangerous, as unworthy, as something that should be infinitely abandoned, there's going to be some wilderness tendency left.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why sensuality problem is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are wilderness tendencies a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's for the very reason that when that same animal doesn't get what it wants, or it gets what it doesn't want, or it loses what it had, or it doesn't have enough for what it desires, it will turn against you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be agitated.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be displeased.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are the one that will pay the price.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why there is no, like, oh, this little sensuality is fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any action, any project, any intention rooted in the desire for the pleasure of the senses, carries that wilderness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, even, well, he compared sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter, like, oh, well, it's not as much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, it's better.
[SPEAKER_01]: To not have as much sensuality, have less.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from the point of view of somebody who wants to be truly, like, free and imperturbable and not liable to suffering, the entire domain, the entire spectrum of sensual intensities needs to be regarded in the same manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's a lot or a little, it's the same like a feces.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even a tiny little bit of feces, it's still
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still shit, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the same smell, same taste, same disgust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's a lot, whether it's little, it's still the same thing that you don't want anything to do with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if, hypothetically, sensuality had absolutely no effect on the wilderness of citta, like to make it more wild, or to keep it wild, or to maintain the underlying tendencies and so on, it would not be a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just would not be an issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like other things, they do not play into that principle of keeping that connection with the wilderness from which you're trying to pull back the elephant, the mind, and tame it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you had no connection to that, there would be no problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And things that don't have connection, they're not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, again, your intention is the most important thing that you need to be perpetually aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the sensations, not the whatever else practices you, but you're currently doing intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that your mind wants?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you losing perspective in regard to that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or are you maintaining the perspective and not allowing it, if it's rooted in these desires of sense pleasures, irritation and so on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's really the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like if you keep an eye on it, then the mind cannot just go there on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you would eventually calm it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as the Sutta say, severed the tendencies of elephant to want to go back to the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And after that, it's like, ah, your citta is pliable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, if you, if you, if you say, directed towards the destruction of taints, the taints are destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Directed towards remembering the past lives, the past lives are remembered.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not before the pliability is developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you might get a right view before the pliability is fully developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not like you've got to fully train the citta before any understanding of dhamma can take place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the understanding of dhamma will gradually start taking place sooner.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you have sotā, pañña, sakadāgāmī, anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the attitude of taming the mind away from the wilderness is an absolute must.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, again, all the suttas, you know, they don't talk in terms of like these
[SPEAKER_01]: Specificities...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure he did, but he hasn't been, like, recorded anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, what... one thing that does remain unchanged is, mind has to be above the hindrances, freed, at least to a degree, eh... sufficiently enough kept away from the wilderness, from the wilderness tendencies, from the hindrances, for the possibility of understanding of the dhamma to take place, if there is right instruction, right reflection, honesty, and everything else we talk about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you have everything else,
[SPEAKER_01]: Honesty, right instruction, right reflection, everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you are not... you haven't sufficiently dried the mind, not just from physical acts of sensuality, but mental intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, none of that will make a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that can make the fire of wisdom light up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's... that's why it's like... it's... it's really, like, not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if people do struggle to, kind of,
[SPEAKER_01]: Say no to sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is definitely helpful to realize why even a little bit of conscious giving into these things carries the same weight, the same implications, and keeps the mind tethered to the same wilderness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sooner or later, if circumstances change, if you lose your composure for one reason or the other, that thread will pull the whole thing back.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you have again the mass of suffering waiting for you that you have to deal with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what the suttas meant, when they said, even like those monks, they were practicing rightly, but then became careless and overly confident, or maybe just complacent, and were satisfied with understanding the dhamma, and taming the mind to a degree, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they chose to go follow desire a little bit, a little bit more, which then led to a little bit more, which led to a little bit more, which then, from their starting point, was actually a lot more now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it says, and that's monks, when then they experience
[SPEAKER_01]: Death or deathly suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering as of those who are dying on account of their mind now reinfected with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't lose the wisdom, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpanna can't lose his wisdom of sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if he becomes careless and starts engaging with sensuality, because, yes, overall, wisdom remains unchanged, the animal is still going to be something he is paired with and something he'll have to put up with, and it's going to be worse for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because somebody who doesn't have perspective, who never experienced correctly count the animal due to the right view and understanding, for them, it's all they know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter the absolutely wild, raging cheetah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of almost every day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's kind of fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't really see the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for somebody who has counted the cheetah enough, saw it, withdraw it from sensuality, dried it up, got the right view, established in that view, and then allows their mind to go back,
[SPEAKER_01]: The discrepancy, it's like dying or pains of... pains of those of dying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's just... it's just like... you can't ignore, obviously, the right context, but you let your mind go back to basically what's... what fully... well, not fully understood, because if it was fully understood, you would... sotāpanna would have not have kind of returned to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it was certainly... the framework of it, of, you know, like the whole... like saṃsāra and the aggregates have been... has been sufficiently understood,
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you let the mind go back into it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, the weight, the impurity of it will be felt a lot worse and a lot more unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's, again, because that principle just cannot change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality always partakes in the wilderness, always keeps the mind wild.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's not uprooted, you always carry the risk of pulling the animal back.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, again, you are the one, you will be the one who has to pay the price for it.